<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honor of chastity A sermon, made and preached by Iohn Featly.</title>
            <author>Featley, John, 1605?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00605</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10741</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101897</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837700</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837700</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2039</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00605)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2039)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 793:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honor of chastity A sermon, made and preached by Iohn Featly.</title>
                  <author>Featley, John, 1605?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G. P[urslowe] for Nicholas Bourne, and are to be sold at his shop, at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chastity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2039:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>OR <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>F <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>STITY.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> made and preached</p>
            <p>BY <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>HN FEATLY.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>amentum nobilium, exaltatio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. <bibl>
                  <hi>Cypr.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the South en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance of the Royall Exchange, 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2039:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2039:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL, Sir THOMAS WARNER, Knight, Super-intendent of the Ilands of Saint <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> and <hi>Metalina,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Carlile</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indiaes,</hi> my much hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red friend, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Oodnes knowe's as well how to accept the ſervice of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, as to merit it. Your <hi>courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> challenge my thanks; and your <hi>love</hi> my affection. J have here
<pb facs="tcp:2039:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> taught the World what J ſhould (rather than what J can) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme. Thus J acknowledge the rules of gratitude; and my deſire to obſerve them. Let it be your <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> to entertaine this expreſsion; your <hi>glory</hi> to countenance it. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this hope, I have ventured upon a <hi>vulgar cenſure:</hi> and what was intended to be <hi>ſtifeled</hi> in an how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, now proſtitutes it ſelfe to an Age. If the ſubiect pleaſe not the Readers, let them remember, <hi>'tis Scripture:</hi> If not the Sermon; J confeſſe <hi>'tis mine.</hi> So all the faults may be favourably corrected, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe freely acknowledged. J that am the Father of this weakeneſſe, profeſſe my ſelfe the admirer of better: and ſhall ſtrive to <hi>imitate</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2039:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> when the ſevereſt <hi>cenſurer</hi> will ſet me a copie. To require a Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of learning and iudgement from the leaſt of the Apoſtles, is to forget diſcretion by expecting a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle. Let the World reſt ſatisfied that (for your ſake) this <hi>atom</hi> is eſpied in the <hi>rayes</hi> of our <hi>Sunne;</hi> and emboldened by your importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. To you therefore I addreſſe my ſelfe, deſiring your acceptance both of this, and the Author,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull Friend to ſerve you, IOHN FEATLY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2039:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2039:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE HONOVR OF CHASTITY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>GENESIS 39.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>How can I doe this great wickedneſſe, and ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Vmane policie is the life of the unſanctified; but religious is the life of the regenerate. The former plotting for the deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full riches of this World; the latter rewarding with a Crowne immortall. 'Tis no taske then of impoſſibility to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine which of the two ſhall beſt deſerve our approbation. For the one (juſt like a Paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſis) giveth light onely to the ſentence of the other. The ſame ſupport's with a bladder on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, expoſed to the hazard of the ſmalleſt flaw; the other is an Arke which carrieth us ſafely to the cape of felicity. <hi>Dignori detur:</hi> Let the honour, then, bee given (not to <hi>Pan,</hi> but) to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:2039:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Apollo;</hi> not to humane devices, but to religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and let each indifferent Judge cenſure that groſſe ear'd <hi>Midas,</hi> whoſe impiety, or igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance devote's him to error. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> (in my Text) ſhall bee the juſt deligate, and arbitrate the matter (contrary to cuſtome) without any ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter corruption. Had not he been as pious to his God, as juſt to his Maſter, he might (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure) have ſtollen a fall through impiety, to deprive him at once, both of chaſtity, and honour. But 'twas the plot of his religion to preſerve him honeſt, that hee might remaine fortunate. Hee that was, at firſt, rejected by his brethren, was received by the <hi>Iſmaelites;</hi> and 'twas the chance of chance to make him happy, when hee expected miſery. His bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage (inſtead of ſervility) became a freedome: His ſlavery was ſoone converted into liberty: And (as if the Sea of his afflictions deemed him too good to be drowned in infelicity) even that helped him to float in the height of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe. None ſo great as <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> now, in the love of the vulgar; in the talke of the greater; or in the heart of his Maſter. Durſt wee to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute this change unto <hi>Fortune,</hi> wee might (with the Poet) juſtly Deifie her. But the great <hi>Iehovah</hi> diſdain's ſuch a no-thing ſhould prove injurious to his Majeſty; and hate's as much the Epicure's deity, as this ſacrifice. <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> was not more highly promoted, than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly diſpoſed; and render's, therefore, his beſt thankes to the God of honour. Yet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2039:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> a ſtrange alteration. That which before exalted him, is now as ready to cry him down. His Miſtreſſe love's him; So doth hee her: Nay ſhe luſt's after him; but ſo will not he her. His conſcience ſweare's him to obedience to the King of Kings, teaching him obſervance to his Miſtreſſe, but onely in things lawfull. Yet cannot hee bee bolder in refuſing, than ſhee in wooing. The redoubt which hee had to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to for an excuſe, was the infidelity to his Maſter, which would have inſued upon it. And (leſt hee ſhould bee taken off from that) be retreates to another of far greater ſtrength, in the words of my Text; <hi>Quomodo facerem malum hoc maximum, &amp; peccarem in Deum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The words are an interrogative objurgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to avoid a more impious temptation: and containe,
<list>
                  <item>1. The Author refuſing, I <hi>Ioſeph.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The action refuſed, aggravated,
<list>
                        <item>1. By the name, <hi>Wickedneſſe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. By the extenſion, <hi>Great.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. The reaſon of the refuſall.
<list>
                        <item>1. In reſpect of the offence, <hi>Sin.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. In reſpect of the obiect, or party offended, <hi>God.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of theſe in their order; and firſt of</p>
            <p>The Author refuſing, <hi>I</hi> Ioſeph.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> When God diſtils his grace into the heart, 'tis ſinnes antidote, and works effectually. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine vertues elevate the ſoule; and diſdaine, as much, a willing conſent to, as the act of ſinne.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2039:6"/> The purity of the Operator contemn's a corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall in the heart, ſolely poſſeſſing that chaire of eſtate: But (if once the malice of tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion purchaſeth entertainment) the former peace was not more delightfull, than the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding warre prove's terrible. The Almighty become's a ſutor, who (not intending to work by his power) wooe's by intreaty: and (as if that Virgin, that chaſt ſoule of man were not worth acceptance, if won without oppoſition) the divel likewiſe aime's at the purchaſe of it to. Happy is that perſon, whoſe reaſon (deſpiſing the falſe allurements) yeeld's a conſent to the God of Gods. Thus was <hi>Ioſeph</hi> wonne by the deity: and his heart was found as conſtant, as the oppoſer turbulent. Had his education nuz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him up in error; or his parents inſtructed him in Idolatry: Had his brethren played with wickedneſſe; or his companions dallied with diſobedience, then the miſt of ignorance might (peradventure) have bred a Cacatact, or drawne a Curtaine over the eyes of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. But ſuch excuſes muſt needs be ſilent, becauſe his education was vertuous, his life religious. <hi>Quo ſemel eſt imbuta recens, &amp;c.</hi> Teach a childe the trade of his youth (ſaye's <hi>Salomon</hi>) and he will not forget it when hee is old. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had learned the principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of his parents; and, therefore, muſt not (nay, cannot) forget them among the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> That Court (which in ſome kinde, was the ſchoole of villany) could never prove guilty
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2039:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> of ſo bad a proficient in ſuch ill and uncivill wayes. But, What do'ſt thou here <hi>Eliah?</hi> What hath <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to doe, that hee dances at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance at the Court? <hi>Exeat aula qui vult eſſe pius.</hi> Mee thinkes that a Cottage in the Country, or a lodge in the Wilderneſſe of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes ſhould have better ſuited with his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious life. Hee knowe's that company may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure a man by ſubtilty, to what they cannot entice him by intreaty: And where did the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell imploy his ſervants more than among King <hi>Pharoahs</hi> houſhold; where wickedneſſe was (with ſome) become their religion, &amp; ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity their common devotion? But (alas) hee was a ſervant, and muſt obey: Yet, where the miſery of bondage ſhall command him to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, the uprightneſſe of his conſcience may repeale the act. It was the Divine providence which raiſed his decayed eſtate, and now ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed his Maſter with the love of his ſlave. Hee that before was ſold by his brethren, is now redeemed from bondage by the hand of his Father. For (behold) God ſuffers him not to live in obſcurity; but give's him ſucceſſe in his endeavours to uſher him to promotion: So that now his Captain begin's to take eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall notice of him; and reward's his fidelity with the command of his houſe. Where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his honour goeth humility; for hee is humbled to his God, before he dare's venture upon command. 'Twas his obedience to God which advanced him; and 'tis the ſervice of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2039:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> that God, which his thoughts entertaine.</p>
            <p>Thus ſhall it be done to the man whom God will honour. The envie of fraternity ſhall be the meanes of promotion, where loyalty to the Divinity petition's for it. Though the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of a brother (upon unjuſt termes) may ſeeme to intreat, yet it can never perſwade the Almighty to curſe, when the malice of the one takes a daring from the devout Religion of the other. Though the ſtrictneſſe of unfeigned zeale, receive's the daily almes of <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, even in theſe wretched times; I meane, nothing but opprobrious calumnies; yet the God of that Zeale will burne up thoſe reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with fire unquenchable. He that fight's under the Colours of pure Religion and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity, ſhall be ſhot-free when he is levell'd at by any reall injurie: Enemies may ſpit the fire of wrath againſt him; yet it ſhall prove as an <hi>ignis fatuus,</hi> to lead themſelves to deſtruction.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> brethren (then) in this Age, I wiſh as much religion as their neglected bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can teach them: and let the bond of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture rectifie their minds, when the preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of anger would ſwell into revenge.</p>
            <p>And to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> himſelfe I wiſh as much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie in obedience, as honour in obſervance; that his divine graces may promote him to happineſſe; and his reſolute perſeverance in his dutie to his GOD, may teach him both to know, and ſhun every ſmal and trifling miſtake in the eyes of the world, becauſe Religion will
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2039:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> write it, <hi>Wickedneſſe;</hi> which is the ſubject of</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>The ſecond generall, the action refuſed, aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, Firſt, by the name,</hi> Wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>The excellency of a curious Picture is the miſty <hi>ſhaddowing</hi> of it: Our Saviour's Eſpouſe (in the <hi>Canticles</hi>) is faire, though <hi>black:</hi> And the night is beſt ſhaped to it's property, when 'tis muffled with it's wonted <hi>darkeneſſe.</hi> But (alas) miſerable man in this onely become's wretched, being <hi>ſhaddowed</hi> with corruptions; <hi>black</hi> with ſinne; and <hi>darke</hi> with wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>Diſobedience is the nature of an unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate perſon, which foile's that grace that ſeek's to wound it; and the divel prove's deſtructive to the man, upon whoſe ground they fight. Had God beene pleaſed as well to forbid the nature of <hi>Adam,</hi> as his perſon ſinning, the ſtrength of his authority would have challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the weakeneſſe of the others reſiſtance; and (without contradiction) have overcome by power, where it would not by intreaty. But (behold,) leſt we ſhould grow too happy by obedience, our fore-father (through unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedneſſe) hurried us unto miſery by an igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant knowledge. Yea, and (leſt miſchiefe ſhould want a miſtreſſe to worke by) <hi>Eve</hi> was the Serpent's hand to offer up to <hi>Adam</hi> the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition for diſobedience. The Divell (as nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the wit of a woman to plot our ruine) became humble, to worke upon her pride; whereby the temptation drew on our deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. <hi>Feminae cum viris habitantes germinant
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2039:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpinas; &amp; arcana mentium acuto mucrone percu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiunt;</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> The female ſexe growe's ſtrong, onely in allurements; and take's off the edge of man's goodneſſe, by a ſharper edge of temptation. Yet (leſt the obſervation ſhould prove too generall, <hi>that the weaker ſexe are continually guilty of the victory) Ioſeph</hi> ſtep's in here to triumph over the intended conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour. His Miſtris, wanting the power of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, diſſolves her ſelfe into ſicke intreaties. But the ſweetneſſe of her lovely complements, diſcover's the uglineſſe of her foule intents. The grace of his Protector burne's in his heart, and light's him to the knowledge of her intended miſchiefe. He that (before) ſeemed to be the object of her love, is (now) poſſeſſed with the hatred of her luſt; and in ſtead of conſenting, conſtrues it <hi>Wickedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I reade the variety of wayes the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell hath projected to ſeduce us to this <hi>Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> I loſe my ſelfe in the Labyrinth; and (ſtrucke dumbe with admiration) ſtrange at the wretchedneſſe of humane frailety. Let me crave your audience and wonder at once, when I name the many filthy wayes of purging this <hi>Wickedneſſe,</hi> by uncleane phyſicke. Eight ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Monſters preſent themſelves unto you, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der theſe titles:</p>
            <p>VIZ.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Fornicatio.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Adulterium.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Stuprum.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Inceſtus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Raptus.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Mollities.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7. <hi>Sodomia.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8. <hi>Beſtialitas.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2039:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>1.<note place="margin">Fornicatio.</note> The firſt of theſe receive's denomination from perſons not matrimonially engaged to a civill converſation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is, —<hi>Sed neſcire me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius.</hi> I would deſcribe theſe deformed Fiends in our Mother tongue: But I hold it fitter to draw <hi>Timanthes</hi> vaile over ſuch a bed of ſnakes, leſt I ſhould teach by reproving. My deſire is, that each of theſe enormities might prove like the Herbe <hi>Anonymos</hi> in <hi>Plinie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin. nat. hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Quae non inveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo nomen invenit;</hi> which got a name by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the nature thereof in obſcurity; rather than the name of the vice ſhould teach the crime.</p>
            <p>Happy was <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> (then) who (knowing the malice of his corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to project a farther miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, if once he had conſented) neglect's the opportunity of yeelding to Adultery, (the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond kind) and terme's that <hi>Wickedneſſe,</hi> which his Miſtris would have judged happineſſe.</p>
            <p>I doubt not (beloved) but that <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample (in my Text) ſhall worke powerfully in you againſt your provocations to uncleanneſſe; and, where deſtruction ſhall crave entertaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (being painted over with a ſeeming plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure) the GOD of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſhall tell you 'tis <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who knowes not the weakneſſe, and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of them which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> termes <hi>ſilly, and laden with divers iniquities?</hi> Who skil's not the cunning of thoſe delicate impoſters, in their wretched devices? As their armes em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2039:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> the neckes of their inchanted captives: ſo doth vengeance their ſoules. They are ſad Ditties which their melodious voices warble out; though the notes bee harmonious: and that deſtruction which they beare about them, is as full of deceit as allurement.</p>
            <p>I feare (beloved) I ſhall not neede to goe farther than to your owne guilty conſciences, for examples of men ſeduced to this impiety. Yet (rather than I will condemne before I can accuſe; or accuſe you without a credible infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation) I will ſearch the Scriptures; where (I am ſure) I ſhall finde <hi>Ruben</hi> intangled with <hi>Bilhah,</hi> his Fathers Concubine: <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.22. <hi>David</hi> with <hi>Bathſheba:</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11. <hi>Herod</hi> with his brother <hi>Philip's</hi> wife: <hi>Mat.</hi> 14. And the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had beene informed, in his firſt Epiſtle to them, 5. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nec Sampſone fortior es,</hi> (as ſaith Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe) nec Davide ſanctior; nec Salomone ſapienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or: Sampſon</hi> excelled thee in ſtrength; <hi>David,</hi> in holineſſe; and <hi>Salomon,</hi> in wiſedome: yet they ſuffered by theſe enticing vanities. Let it be your pious induſtrie to be taught both by examples and precepts, that ye may be crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the glory of coeleſtiall bliſſe.</p>
            <p>Yet let not him expect the Diadem, which juſtifie's himſelfe, being preſerved from the act of this <hi>wickedneſſe</hi> onely by compulſion: For, (as Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> gravely adviſeth us) <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fida cuſtos caſtitatis eſt neceſſitas; &amp; ille verè pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus dicendus eſt, cui licuit peccare, ſed noluit:</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:2039:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> Neceſſity is a faithleſſe preſerver of Integritie; and he onely is truely termed chaſte, who may fall, and will not. Thus doth <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſtand excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for he leave's (in a manner) the poſſibility of ſinning, by a religious reſiſtance.</p>
            <p>To every <hi>Ioſeph</hi> here (then) let me preferre the example of him in my Text: If ſuperiors en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice you, refuſe them; if inferiours, diſdaine them; if equals, ſhunne them. Let not the complexion of the vice ſteale credit to the <hi>Lie;</hi> but correct the fury of it by a pious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaguing.</p>
            <p>And, to <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> Miſtris, here, I muſt, in all humility, tender this advice to her petulant diſpoſition: Let her neither inſnare the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous by her painted hypocriſie; nor her <hi>Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels</hi> face intrap the ignorant: Let not her Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren ſongs ſteale to the eares of any, on whom ſhe deſires to ſurfeit with incontinency: But let her praiers rather cruſh thoſe deſires, and her devotion repell them. Religion is the beſt remedy againſt ſuch ſwelling tumors of impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety; and the very remembrance that it is <hi>wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe,</hi> nay, <hi>great wickedneſſe,</hi> may controule the vice; if every one in particular determine with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in my Text, <hi>How can I doe this great wickedneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Which is</p>
            <p>The ſecond part of my ſecond Generall, The acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on refuſed, aggravated, Secondly, By the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion, <hi>Great.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſuetudo peccandi tollit ſenſum peccati:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senec.</note> (ſaith
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2039:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> the divine Philoſopher:) He that ſell's himſelfe to the cuſtome of diſloyalty to his Creator, become's ignorant of his offence; and, inſtead of correction, prove's unskilfull in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his ſinne. The gluttonous ſatiety of our ſwelling Guliſts, argue's their neceſſity of offending by forgetfulnes: and their own abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance barr's them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the juſt weighing of the poverty of the diſtreſſed. The common drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard cannot be taken with a due thankſ-giving for that ſuperfluity which he corrupt's, from whence many thirſtie ſoules might ſucke a reaſonable ſupply for neceſſity. How then can we determine of any Religion to be found in him, who (inclined to this <hi>great</hi> wickedneſſe mentioned in my Text) borrow's his provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from new-found compoſitions?</p>
            <p>We are all beleaguered by our home-bred enemies: but eſpecially by Saint <hi>Paul's</hi> three ſquadrons; <hi>The luſt of the fleſh; The luſt of the eye;</hi> and <hi>The pride of life.</hi> Hee that loſeth but the leaſt ground, upon neceſſity, to either of theſe, ſuffer's in the retreat; and (unleſſe hee gathereth ſtrength by the power of grace) can never recover what he hath loſt. <hi>Inter omnia certamina Chriſtianorum, ſola dura ſunt praelia caſtitatis; ubi quotidiana eſt pugna, &amp; rara victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. l. de hom. c <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Yee may be pleaſed to obſerve both the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie and progreſſe of this ſinne. 'Twas begun in Paradiſe incluſively, though not actually,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2039:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> by the fall of <hi>Adam.</hi> 'Tis haereditary to all of Vs the off-ſpring of him: For, <hi>Libido quâdam lege naturae in ſcelus erumpit;</hi> as <hi>Hieron.</hi> hath it.<note place="margin">Hier. in Ep. ad Fieriam.</note> And (without repentance) it muſt be puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in Hell. The firſt enticing is grounded either upon neceſſity; or pleaſure; or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon both: At which preſent (if GOD be not pleaſed to guide the heart) the ſinne is purchaſed, though not yet acted. Then is the Divell, for the moſt part, rhetoricall; and perſwade's by inſinuating arguments for his owne advantage. Trifles ſeldome breake friendſhip betweene the enticer and the allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and what in it ſelfe is impious, hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade's to be a very ſleight (or rather no) ſin. Thus, if the heart conſent, the Divel's proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte is wonne: And (leſt he ſhould know what deſtruction he plunge's himſelfe into) hee's kept in ignorance by <hi>that God of this World, who blinde's the eyes of his underſtanding, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpell of CHRIST, which is the Image of GOD, ſhould ſhine unto him:</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>But, ô that ineffable, and moſt dreadfull ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quel which enſue's upon the firſt conſent! That which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> here accompt's a <hi>great</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, the forlorne creature either not knowe's, or not value's. While he was totte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, he halted (as it were) betweene two opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions; for the grace of his Protector withſtood the oppoſer: But ſo ſoone as the weake under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding had ſurrendred to the will, the ſinne
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2039:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> was entertained; yet that 'twas a ſinne, or a <hi>great</hi> wickedneſſe, was kept concealed. <hi>Facilis diſcenſus averni, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis then an eaſie matter to haſten to the pit of deſtruction, when the Divell drive's a man by his hourely provoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But, alas miſerable wretch! ſhall the fire of thy luſt burne within thee, and not the fire of hell burne for thee? Shalt thou caſt thy ſelfe into that deepe ditch, (as <hi>Salomon</hi> calleth an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultreſſe: <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.27.) for thy pleaſure; and not expect a deeper ditch of deſtruction for thy paine? Shall the flaſhes of this <hi>great</hi> wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe dazle thine eyes; and not the flaſhes of hell terrifie thy conſcience? Earthly plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures (me think's) in reaſon cannot, or (at leaſt) ſhould not delight us; becauſe they are of no continuance. Before they come, we conſume our ſelves with a longing deſire, and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them. When they are preſent, if they continue long, they cloy us: if they flye ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, they torment us. And, when they are paſt, we may hang downe our heads with the conſideration of Saint <hi>Paul's Quaere, What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit had yee then in thoſe things whereof ye are now aſhamed?</hi> for the end of them is death.</p>
            <p>Diſeaſes (yee know) are the common re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of the fleſh in this life: and, for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, there ſhall not want the terrors, and gnawings of a guilty conſcience. Oh the hideous skreeches which the heart vent's in unmeaſured ſobs! Oh the diſmall affirights
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2039:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> which the darkneſſe of the night preſent's to the fancy of an impious adulterer! Oh that ill-boading noiſe, and fearefull croaking which this creature heare's, yet knowe's not how, or where, or whence! His conſcience is ſicke of the wormes: His underſtanding ſtifled in clowdes of miſt: His will ruſhe's him head-long to the whirle-poole of deſtruction: and (leſt his body ſhould bee forgotten behinde) that crawle's upon the very diſeaſes which it hath gotten, and ſo ſtalke's to confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Erre not,</hi> then, <hi>my beloved brethren,</hi> (as St. <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith) neither fall into the tallons of your untutored luſts. Subject not your ſelves to the ſlavery of temptation; but determine, with the Father, that <hi>Leviſſima cogitatio pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candi fit peccatum;</hi> The ſmalleſt and fineſt-ſpun thought of ſinning is an offence. What, then, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> (in my Text) hath termed <hi>great,</hi> call not thou ſmall. What he hath determined to be ſtiled <hi>wickedneſſe,</hi> doe not thou boaſt of with impudence; but correct thy libidinous motions with the words of my Text. <hi>Levia ſunt, ſed multa ſunt,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine:</hi> Theſe ſins (peradventure) may ſeeme ſmall to thee, yet they are many; and will oppreſſe thee as much by their number, as others by their weight.</p>
            <p>That this offence then (which belongeth chiefly to our purpoſe) is not wickedneſſe, who dares affirme? Or that 'tis <hi>great,</hi> who can deny? <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> is ſo ſenſible of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2039:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>greatneſſe</hi> of it, that he propoſeth a queſtion, touching a branch thereof, ſeeming very trivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in appearance; yet of greater conſequence than a common judgement will cenſure it: <hi>An in amplexibus, &amp; oſculis conſiſtat peccatum mortale?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho. Aqu. in <hi>2.</hi> ſecundae q. <hi>154.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Whether a mortall ſinne may not couch it ſelfe under our common greetings? And he reſolve's the queſtion thus; <hi>Secundum ſuam rationem non nominant peccatum mortale: Si autem fiant propter delectationem luxuriae, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur libidinoſa, &amp; ſunt peccata mortalia.</hi> Thoſe kinde of complements (of themſelves) ſuffer not the name of ſinnes: But if their aime bee luxurious, their end is pernitious. If then our very ſalutations, and common greetings (ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, onely, in impure veſſels) may gather dregs, and ſo be turned into corruption: What are thoſe more impious acts which, ſwelling in our hearts, breake forth into wickedneſſe? Might not <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> upon grounds ſufficiently warranted, aggravate the offence by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion of it, and conclude it a <hi>great</hi> wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Great</hi> indeed, in the firſt place on his owne part if you conſider him:</p>
            <p>Firſt, meerely as a man; ſhould hee have thus treſpaſſed with any of the leaſt, the worſt, the pooreſt of women.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as a man in honour, in the ſame houſe. Juſtly might his fidelity have beene ſtained with infamy, had his Captain's cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie been rewarded with ſuch an injury.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2039:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And thirdly, as a childe of Grace; whoſe fall (had he yeelded) might have proved more deſtructive to his ſoule, than his former honor could gaine him affection. But indeed, (as if his integrity grew too wiſe to forget the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuch an errour) he could not eaſily fall, leſt his example ſhould teach his inferiours to be guilty of the like: or the noiſe of the fact command the people to ſcorne him. For, whom we ſuſpect guilty of ſo great an offence, we ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cruſh with our bluſhes, than maintaine by our induſtrie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> 
               <hi>Great,</hi> againe, on her part too. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> If his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's wife ſhould have proſtituted her ſelfe to her ſervant, her vaſſall; the cenſure of her crime would freely have paſſed; and each common inferiour would have become her Judge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, If to one whom ſhee loved, the ſinne had beene the greater. For, who know's not that God, in his Juſtice, hath puniſhed the fact here on earth, at leaſt, with a mutuall hatred betweene the delinquents; ſo that (like to that of <hi>Tamar</hi> and <hi>Amnon</hi>) the future hatred wherewith ſhe would have hated him, might have beene greater than the love wherewith ſhe had loved him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>great</hi> in reſpect of her greatneſſe alſo, by the Poet's cenſure;
<q>
                  <l>Omne animi vitium tanto conſpectius in ſe</l>
                  <l>Crimen habet, &amp;c. —</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:2039:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> Enormities are built up higher, and grow more eminent, when their foundation is the errour of an eminent perſon. And <hi>Iſiodore</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der's the reaſon of it: <hi>Creſcit enim delicti cumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus; &amp; quod minoribus ignoſcitur, majoribus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putatur:</hi> For the fault (ſay's hee) increaſeth: and the loftie Cedars are viewed by all, when they are ſhaken; whileſt the neglected ſhrubs are not regarded.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> 
               <hi>Great,</hi> againe, not in reſpect of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> the Favourite of his Maſter, onely: or his Miſtris the wife of his Maſter: but alſo, in reſpect of the offence, chiefly conſidered in it ſelfe, that it is a <hi>ſinne:</hi> Which is</p>
            <p>The firſt part of my third Generall, The reaſon of the refuſall; Firſt, in reſpect of the offence, <hi>Sinne:</hi> How can I doe this great wickednes, and <hi>ſinne,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This part of my Text command's me to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract ſome-thing out of no-thing. For my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe muſt be of a privation; and that which onely hath gotten a name, muſt teach us our proper nature. I am fallen here, upon <hi>ſinne;</hi> yet without offence (I hope): and ſhall intreat thereof without treſpaſſing on your patience. My Text give's me not authority to be tedious in the generality, leſt I ſhould neglect this which it doeth chiefly particularize. Curious Schoole-diſtinctions I could, but will not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you with; leſt the time denie me your at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and the niceneſſe your acceptance.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2039:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> Let it ſuffice that I walke in the vulgar tract, and divide <hi>ſinne</hi> onely into <hi>originall</hi> and <hi>actuall.</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The former include's both a falling from God in the loynes of <hi>Adam;</hi> and the evill which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it: which is, as well the defect of origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall good in the ſoule, and body; as the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of evill inſtead of that originall good, in both.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond, which is <hi>Actuall,</hi> is either <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall,</hi> or <hi>externall: ſpirituall,</hi> or <hi>carnall:</hi> of <hi>omiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> or <hi>commiſſion: infirmity,</hi> or <hi>preſumption, &amp;c.</hi> as your daily Sermons inſtruct you.</p>
            <p>To our purpoſe, then, I muſt confine my ſelfe to the intention of my Theame. Where I finde, that if <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had ſinned according to his temptation, it might have beene a great <hi>actuall ſinne,</hi> committed (perhaps) with <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption;</hi> and ſeverely to be puniſhed by the rod of Heaven. It was (therefore) the mercy of our jealous God, to vouchſafe him aſſiſtance in his greateſt temptations. Thus, a <hi>man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in honour, was of underſtanding, that hee might not bee compared to the beaſts that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had he himſelfe beene the tempter, and ſhe denyed, his <hi>ſinne</hi> had beene entertained by the firſt extravagancie of his words: <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p>Had hee wooed, and ſhee conſented; the miſchiefe had doubled it ſelfe by the act.</p>
            <p>Had he ſecretly deſired her, and not diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the fire; yet <hi>Athanaſius</hi> would cenſure him in his <hi>Qui formam concupiſcit, quamvis ſine
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2039:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> faſcinore, peccatum ſine teſte commiſit.</hi> Hee that deſire's the beauty, yet not foulely enjoying it; hath committed a <hi>ſinne,</hi> though without a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Or (if you pleaſe) the Scripture ſhall better Engliſh it in that <hi>Whoſoever looketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a woman to luſt after her, hath committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery with her in his heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here (peradventure) I have onely, as yet, awakened the conſcience of <hi>Ioſeph's Miſtris;</hi> whileſt the reſt applaud themſelves in their ſeeming integrity. But (alas beloved) I muſt ſummon you all to the Court of Conſcience; and (it may be) find them guilty, which are moſt confident in their juſtification. For I muſt diſtinguiſh of a two-fold adultery, both <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> and <hi>Spirituall.</hi> The former ye have heard me hitherto treat of. The latter is two-fold:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, <hi>Metaphoricall;</hi> which is any <hi>ſinne,</hi> of what nature and condition ſoever: becauſe our ſoules are eſpouſed to Chriſt; which the Scripture termeth <hi>ſpirituall whoredome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond conſiſteth in the abuſe of any holy thing; which is <hi>adultery,</hi> by way of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> will have it.</p>
            <p>Not to enter into a ſtrict examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your hearts, or common application, which your guiltineſſe (I ſuppoſe) hath already prevented me of; Let me keepe to the purpoſe of this word as it is in my Text.</p>
            <p>Yee have hitherto ſeen the diverſity of <hi>ſinne;</hi> and the monſtrous birth of this wee treate of. Let <hi>Iſiodor</hi> now have leave to preſent you with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2039:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ladder, by which this impious vice climbs up to heaven to call for vengeance. <hi>Cogitatio prava</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>delectationem parit; delectatio conſenſionem; conſenſio actionem; actio conſuetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem; conſuetudo neceſſitatem; &amp; neceſſitas mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi> Evill thoughts beget delight; delight a conſent; conſent the act; the act cuſtome; cuſtome neceſſity; and neceſſity death. Saint <hi>Iames</hi> make's but three rounds to this Ladder: <hi>Luſt, when it conceiveth, bringeth forth ſinne; and ſinne, when it is finiſhed bringeth forth death.</hi> But hee that hath a deſire to walke more lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurely to his deſtruction, and (in ſpight of the Spirit of grace) will follow his owne unbridled luſts, may travell in thoſe eight by-paths of iniquity mentioned formerly; and ſo build up the mighty <hi>Babel</hi> of his owne <hi>confuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>ſiſte paulum viator,</hi> as <hi>Minutius Felix</hi> ſpeaketh in another kind. Stay thou that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt in thoſe uncouth paths, while I queſtion thee with S. <hi>Bernard, Quare peccas, &amp;c.</hi> Why doeſt thou <hi>ſinne</hi> thus, O thou unjuſt creature? Why doeſt thou offend, O thou miſerable wretch? The all-ſeeing providence eſpie's out all thy waies; and the darkeſt Cells, and fowleſt cavernes of thy ſooty heart lye open, and manifeſt to his piercing eyes. Plead not the unchaſt allurements of laſcivious women which tempt thee, for an excuſe: For our age returne's it ſelfe guilty of ſuch helliſh inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; ſuch <hi>Philtra,</hi> and <hi>Diaſatyrions;</hi> ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and potions to cheriſh this abortive brat
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2039:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> of uncleanneſſe, that they ſeeme even to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the ſeverall allurements of the weaker ſexe by more horrid, and divelliſh inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Paſcitur libido conviviis,</hi> (ſay's Saint <hi>Ambroſe) nutritur deliciis; vino accenditur, &amp; ebrietate inflammatur.</hi> This is not to learn of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> to <hi>beat downe our bodies, and keepe them in ſubiection:</hi> Nor of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in my Text; to contend with the temptation, becauſe to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, is to <hi>ſinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe; he that ſeeke's to excuſe himſelfe by the ſuperfluous humours of a pampered body, ſhould rather (with <hi>Lazarus</hi>) live by the <hi>crummes,</hi> than <hi>fare</hi> ſo <hi>deliciouſly</hi> with glutto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous <hi>Dives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> report's of <hi>Antiochus</hi> King of <hi>Aſia,</hi> that when he was invited to performe a viſit to the faire <hi>Panthea</hi> by the various reports of her admired beauty, refuſed to goe; replying, <hi>Si modo illam convenero quum per otium vacat, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe illa mihi perſuaſura eſt, ut, neglectis regni ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiis, illam conveniam quum etiam non vacat.</hi> If (ſay's he) I ſhould repaire unto her now my leaſure ſerve's mee, perhaps ſhee will ſo take me by her alluring forme, that when I ſhould follow the affaires of my Kingdome, I ſhould ſpend my time with her when I have no lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>I read that <hi>Dioniſius</hi> diſ-inherited his ſonne, which was heire to his Kingdome, for defiling himſelfe with another man's wife.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Egyptians</hi> puniſhed the adulterer with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2039:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> a thouſand ſtripes, and the adultereſſe with the loſſe of her noſe. A puniſhment continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſince to divers (not by <hi>Egyptian</hi> edict, to the women onely; but by the Indian diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe) even many times, to both the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents.</p>
            <p>If theſe examples, which are fetch't from prophane Authors, want the power and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of perſwading you to ſhun this <hi>ſinne</hi> in my Text: let then <hi>the Word of God (which is ſharper than any two-edged Sword) divide between the ioynts, and the marrow</hi> of him that <hi>run's on ſtill in this wickedneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſo committeth adultery with a woman,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon) lacketh underſtanding: hee that doth it, deſtroyeth his owne ſoule, Proverbs</hi> 6.32.</p>
            <p>By the <hi>Leviticall</hi> Law,<note place="margin">Levit. 20.10.</note> 
               <hi>the adulterer and adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſe were both put to death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi</hi> were <hi>both thruſt through by Phinehas, even in the tent, Num.</hi> 25.8.</p>
            <p>Yea, and twenty and five thouſand of the <hi>Benjamites</hi> were <hi>ſlain in battaile by the Iſraelites, Iudg.</hi> 20.46.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What ſhall I ſay then? Thinke yee</hi> (my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved) <hi>that either Zimri and Cozbi; or thoſe twenty and five thouſand of the Benjamites were greater</hi> adulterers <hi>than any</hi> of our age? <hi>I tell yee nay; but except yee repent, yee ſhall all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe periſh.</hi> The Canon of the Law runne's <hi>Paritas dilicti paritatem poenae requirit.</hi> Thoſe muſt equally ſhare in their puniſhments,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:2039:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> which have been equally guilty of an offence. If thoſe, before mentioned, ſuffered for their luſts in ſo high a degree; 'twere but juſtice in God to puniſh us in the like nature as (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther worſe than) them.</p>
            <p>Goe then thou guilty conſcience; <hi>ſinne no more, leſt a worſe</hi> puniſhment than theſe <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen unto thee. As thou haſt yeelded the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſervants unto uncleanneſſe, and to iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty unto iniquity: even ſo now yeeld thy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſervants to righteouſneſſe unto holineſſe, and thy end ſhall bee everlaſting peace.</hi> Learne of good <hi>Ioſeph</hi> here, to ſhunne this ſpirituall <hi>Adder</hi> which ſting's thy ſoule, and then hiſſe's at thee for thy folly. Let God be the object of all our deſires; the moderator of our thoughts; and the controller of our actions; ſo, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever rebellious thought ſteale's into our fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, he will correct it, by diſcovering it unto us to bee <hi>ſinne</hi> againſt his ſacred Majeſty. <hi>In ſole etiam leviſſimi pulvuſculi cernuntur,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> When the Sunne ſhine's into a Chamber through any crevice, the ſmalleſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes are diſcerned by it: So when the grace of the Sunne of glory ſhine's into our hearts wee ſhall eaſily diſcover the ſmalleſt allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to this impurity; and ſuddainly then may we ſeek for help, when we finde it to be a <hi>ſinne againſt God;</hi> which is</p>
            <p>The laſt part of my laſt generall; The reaſon of <hi>Ioſeph's</hi> refuſall in reſpect, Secondly, of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2039:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> object, or party offended, <hi>God.</hi> How can I doe, &amp;c?</p>
            <p>To queſtion a Deity is to wound it: nay, to ſuſpect it, onely, is to deny it. The hearts of men are the Booke of God: wherein his Majeſty is written (for the moſt part) in ſo ſmall a character, that it dazel's the eyes of their underſtandings which attempt to prie into it. He that ſit's in the high, and holy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hath commanded all to the knowledge, and ſervice of himſelfe. Ignorance, therefore, of his ſacred Majeſty (although it may ſeeme to pleade an excuſe in ſome, yet it) can be at the moſt but <hi>a tanto,</hi> not <hi>a toto,</hi> as the Schoolmen ſpeake. For <hi>hee hath not left himſelfe without witneſſe, in that hee doth good, and giveth us raine from heaven, and fruitfull ſeaſons; fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our hearts with food and gladneſſe, Acts.</hi> 14.17. Whatſoever, therfore, is endued with a reaſonable ſoule, cannot chooſe but deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine of a ſupernaturall power. <hi>Caelum ipſum vide quam latè tenditur, quam rapidè volvitur, &amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Minucius Felix</hi> hath it: and the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſhall be the interpreter: <hi>The heavens declare the glory of God; and the Firmament ſheweth his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di-worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not labour your eares with the many and vulgar arguments to prove a God, as if I were to catechiſe a congregation of Infidels. Let me only preſent you with one of the ſame Author, which (I hope) ſhall command your
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2039:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> attention, and approbation. Let us conſider our ſelves as we are men; and view the variety of faces (which we daily behold) with a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable eye; and obſerve how we are loſt in the admiration of ſo much diſſimilitude in our likeneſſes.<note place="margin">Min. Felix.</note> 
               <hi>Similes univerſi videmur; &amp; inter ſe ſinguli diſſimiles invenimur:</hi> We ſeeme all (among our ſelves) like one the other; and yet are we found (in ſome thing or other) each un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the other. Which demonſtrate's unto us the wonderfull worke of a ſuperior Power to be magnified in this variety.</p>
            <p>The Heathens, in ancient times, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the <hi>Quod ſit,</hi> in the poſitive deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of a divine Commander: although they erred in the <hi>Quid ſit,</hi> as well as the <hi>Quis ſit;</hi> what he hee was, as who hee was. And I can juſtifie, by mine owne experience, that the <hi>Salvages</hi> in the Weſterne <hi>Indiaes</hi> (at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) have a generall tradition received from their Anceſtors, which teache's them as far in Divinity, as ſome of the former Heathen had learned; even that there is a great Controller above, who doth never injure them: yet they ſacrifice to the Devill, becauſe they feele his frequent correction.</p>
            <p>I taxe not our times for a worſe (than ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage) ignorance: although (with ſorrow I ſpeake it) I feare here are ſome, even among us, <hi>Qui non tam Dei nomen, quam ipſum Deum ignorant:</hi> which are not ignorant of the name, but the attributes of God. Let it not then bee
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2039:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> accounted a digreſſion, if I give the ſame <hi>Minu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> leave to inſtruct ſuch ignorant Chriſtians in the properties of their <hi>unknowne</hi> GOD. <hi>Vniverſa quaecunque ſunt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>verbo jubet, ratione diſpenſat, virtute conſummat, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis hee which commandeth all things which are, by his Word; order's them by his reaſon; and perfect's them by his vertue. <hi>Hic nec videri po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt; viſu clarior eſt: nec comprehendi; tactu pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior eſt: nec aeſtimari; ſenſibus major eſt; Infini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, immenſus; &amp; ſoli ſibi tantus, quantus eſt, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus.</hi> He is ſuch a GOD as cannot be ſeene, (to convict the worſhippers of beaſts, and the like) becauſe he is cleerer than our ſight: Nor can hee be comprehended, (to confute our <hi>Labans</hi> with their <hi>ſtolne gods</hi>) becauſe he is too pure to be touched: Nor can he be ſufficiently va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued, (to convince our Libertines, which ſerve him after their common, triviall, and irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner) becauſe hee is greater than our ſenſes can determine him to be. He is infinite, immenſe: yea, what he truely is, is only truely knowne to himſelfe. <hi>Sic eum dignè aeſtimamus, dum inaeſtimabilem dicimus:</hi> So that wee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme him moſt, when wee conclude him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable.</p>
            <p>But, this way to diſcourſe of GOD, is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly commanded by my Text. We are here to looke upon him with the eyes of our minds more directly, either as a ſin-revenging GOD; and ſo learne to avoid uncleanneſſe, becauſe 'tis a ſinne <hi>againſt</hi> GOD, who will <hi>wound the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2039:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> heads of his enemies, and the hairie ſcalpe of ſuch a one as goeth on ſtill in his wickedneſſe:</hi> Or elſe, as an <hi>indulgent Father:</hi> and ſo learn to ſhun all <hi>appearance</hi> of this <hi>evill,</hi> becauſe it is a ſinne <hi>againſt GOD,</hi> who is ſo loving to us; and requires no requitall at all, but our reciprocall love (in our obedience) to him.</p>
            <p>Should not <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> then, have beene juſtly queſtioned, if (in this conflict) his Miſtreſſe's temptation had over ſwayed his religion, to taxe him with ignorance, or forgetfulneſſe of the Lord his Maker? If neither a filiall, nor a ſervile feare of this <hi>GOD,</hi> could have reigned his unbridled appetite? To the prevention whereof (yee ſee) 'tis the onely ſpell which he charme's the firie devill, in his Miſtreſſe, with, <hi>How can I doe this great wickedneſſe, and ſinne AGAINST GOD?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let not us then (beloved) who know the <hi>GOD</hi> of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> by his attributes; yea, and are trained up in the wayes of his ſervice, <hi>ſubject our ſelves</hi> to the <hi>bondage</hi> of our corruptions. Let not the affectation of, nor the ſmalleſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to, the leaſt ſinne, rob us of our ſervice to the greateſt <hi>GOD;</hi> but let us reaſon with our temptations in the words of my Text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paula</hi> the Matron is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended by S. <hi>Hierom,</hi> that, <hi>Ita levia deflevit peccata, ut grandiſſimorum crederes ream:</hi> She did ſo bewaile her ſmalleſt ſinnes, that ſhe ſeemed (by her zealous repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) to be guilty of the greateſt.</p>
            <p>Servants we are to <hi>GOD: Let us therefore</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2039:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> commandeth) <hi>be obedient to our Maſter in all things.</hi> Sonnes we are of <hi>GOD:</hi> let us <hi>tender,</hi> therefore, <hi>our duties to him,</hi> as he himſelfe require's, and enable's us to performe it; leſt he queſtion us in his owne words; <hi>If I be a Father, where is mine honour? If I be a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, where is my feare? ſaith the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rege, ergo, tuos adfectus; dirige actus; corrige greſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus:</hi> (as ſaith <hi>Bonaventure:</hi>) Subdue, then, thine affections; direct thy actions; and correct thy ſteps, that thou maiſt not tread out of this path which <hi>Ioſeph</hi> hath led thee in; checking thine oppoſer upon all aſſaults, with, <hi>How can I doe this great wickedneſſe, and ſinne againſt GOD?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto have I endeavoured to handle each particular part of my Text, ſeverally. Your at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention hath now given me aſſurance of your acceptance: and (to gratifie you) I muſt crave your patience a ſecond time. I am ingaged to looke backe upon my Text, once more, before I can leave it: and in the firſt part, [which is, <hi>The Author, Ioſeph</hi>] I muſt beſeech you to conſider, His place of honour, from a low e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate: His place of juſtice, guided by diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And his place of providence, to ſtore for a future neceſſity. Here is true honour, begot by wiſedome; borne by obſervance; and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by honeſty.</p>
            <p>Againe; Here's the ſome of envie from his brethren, wiped cleane off by the love of his GOD.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2039:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Moreover; Here's poverty, and bondage, (without repining) climb'd up into riches and freedome (yet without pride, or ambition.)</p>
            <p>Beſides; Here's patience in adverſitie; and faithfulneſſe in ſervilitie. Here is humility in honour; and piety in plenty.</p>
            <p>If his example winne us not in any of theſe; wee'll proceed to the ſecond part, <hi>[The action refuſed.]</hi> Here (I am certaine) none can want admonition.</p>
            <p>None of the eight ſorts of uncleanneſſe write our <hi>Ioſeph</hi> guilty. Hee denie's, though his Miſtreſſe intreat's. Here's GOD, and the Devill contending for a ſoule. The woman (who firſt tempted man) exerciſe's her autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againe, in <hi>Potipher's</hi> wife: but GOD (who is greater) command's by his ſupremacie. Here's the wickedneſſe of a woman, and the goodneſſe of a man, poſitively: And againe, here's the goodneſſe of a woman, <hi>(as ſome will have it)</hi> and the wickedneſſe of a man, inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively. Here Vertue and vice are at contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Here's the ſulfureous fire of Hell burning in luſt; and the power of Heaven quenching the flame. Here's a conflict betweene Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and Adulterie; but Religion become's the Judge. Here's a controverſie in Law, but Piety is the Vmpire. And (laſtly) here's fire and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter meeting together in a ſtrong contention: but the <hi>Spirit of God breathes upon the water.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See here how oppoſition adde's glory to the triumpher. Had not <hi>Ioſeph</hi> beene tempted, he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2039:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> had not beene proved: But (being tempted) had he conſented, he had not beene accepted. How knew he, but that it might be policie in his Miſtris, to allure him to wickedneſſe not intended to be acted, that ſhe might depoſe him from honour, whom perhaps ſhee hated?</p>
            <p>To prevent an injury (therefore) in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, hee diſdained the power of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe's temptation. 'Twas enough that hee knew her a <hi>woman,</hi> and therein her infirmities: although he remembred ſhee was his Miſtris, and therefore inſtruct's her.</p>
            <p>A vertuous Woman is like the <hi>Iewell in the field,</hi> mentioned in the Goſpell: Or as the <hi>Sunne</hi> in the Heavens, dazeling the eyes of the weake ſpectators: and giving luſtre to the reſt of her ſexe, the <hi>ſmalleſt Starres.</hi> Yea, a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in honour (inveſted with the <hi>Ermins</hi> of Religion) is all white, and goodneſſe of her ſelfe: though not without ſome blacke ſpots of malice and corruption. But (on the other ſide) a Woman in honour, ſupported by pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, leaning upon command, and yet bending double with vice; is witty in her revenge; dangerous in her malice; contemning the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous; and (in a furious rapture) plotting for miſchiefe on thoſe who ſell not their very ſoules to content her humour. Doe but obſerve the wife of <hi>Potipher,</hi> and yee may finde it her trueſt character.</p>
            <p>But (on the other partie) Religion is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant, though contemned: for <hi>great wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:2039:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> ready to be performed by great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, (if it had not beene controuled by piety) would have broke out into deſtruction. Had ſhe onely loved him, it had been her courteſie. Had ſhe loved his Religion onely, it had been her goodneſſe. Had ſhe loved onely his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, it had beene her diſcretion. Had ſhee loved only his humility, it had bin her honor. But in her love (which was but the counterfeit of her luſt) ſhe diſcovered her wilfull impurity. <hi>Origo quidem amoris honeſta eſt; ſed magnitudo deformis;</hi> ſaith <hi>Hierom.</hi> The ſparkes of love are honeſt; but the flames are dangerous. If any here have beene ſcorched with them, let the teares of contrition quench the fire; &amp; the GOD of that contrition accept the repentance.</p>
            <p>Hitherto I have onely touched upon that <hi>Adultery</hi> which is <hi>carnall,</hi> mentioned former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. I muſt now looke backe upon that which is <hi>ſpirituall</hi> alſo. S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaking of ſome Virgins that were Votaries, ſaye's they were <hi>adulterae priuſquam nuptae;</hi> adultereſſes before they were wedded to that auſtere life, although they were Virgins: and he explaines himſelfe preſently after, ſaying; <hi>Not to any husband, but to</hi> CHRIST. O that wee could once bee free from this whoredome; and become like the <hi>Kings Daughter</hi> in the <hi>Pſalmes, All glorious with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in!</hi> O that our ſoules were clad in <hi>white robes of innocencie;</hi> and not in the <hi>menſtruous rags</hi> of our naturall corruptions! O that a <hi>ſeared con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> might not perſwade us to a <hi>drowſie ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:2039:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> in a <hi>ſeeming honeſty,</hi> when theſe <hi>Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of fleſh</hi> cannot be truly free'd from <hi>impiety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoever ſinne we commit, is in it ſelfe a <hi>great wickedneſſe;</hi> and the Apoſtle tell's us, that <hi>the wages thereof is death.</hi> Our mortality, then, teacheth us the puniſhment of our diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, much more therefore ought our lives to inſtruct us in repentance. Our ſinnes are committed againſt a mighty <hi>Iehovah, the LORD ſtrong and mighty;</hi> and yet <hi>our GOD.</hi> Which put's me in mind of my third and laſt part.</p>
            <p>Quarels among men may be taken up by the amity of friends: But ſinnes againſt God, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by enmity with our ſelves. If then, <hi>Ioſeph</hi> refuſed to admit of a conſpiracie againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and put it off divinely, leſt he ſhould <hi>ſinne againſt GOD:</hi> How much more ought wee, whoſe ſlackneſſe in righteouſneſſe condemne's us to be leſſe religious. The <hi>leaſt</hi> here hath not <hi>Ioſeph's command;</hi> nor the <hi>greateſt</hi> (I feare) his <hi>goodneſſe:</hi> Let <hi>all</hi> contend for his <hi>honeſty.</hi> What vice ſoever beg's for entertainment, wil be beſt anſwered in the words of my Text; if each par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon reply, <hi>How can I doe this great wickedneſſe, and ſinne againſt God?</hi> To which <hi>God,</hi> the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, bee all praiſe, honor, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
